hey welcome to Brandon sanderson's 2025
writing science fiction fantasy lectures
today we're going to cover plot
specifically the ideas of Promise
progress and payoff so I hope you enjoy
the lecture we'll be on plot next week
as well hey everybody Welcome to class
it's science fiction fantasy writing
[Applause]
yay because this is a year where we're
recording it I am on the ball and have
uh outlined the rest of the semester for
you so you can see what's coming up uh
and I guess if you're planning to uh I
don't know go to Ruba one week you can
pick the week you're least uh engaged by
um so there will be two guest
lectures uh usually I have two uh first
one's going to be on the February 6th
and the second one will be on February
27th um so we aren't 100% sure who those
people will be yet but I think maybe
we'll try to get uh Indie publishing
people the second one is we are a little
closer to the publishing lectures and
we'll see who we uh who we bring in for
uh for talking about character so uh
that's what we're going to doing like I
told you last time we're going to go uh
three weeks on each topic and uh your
questions that you write down in your
take your quiz by 845 we will save those
for the Q&A
lecture um and that's when I will try to
dig into those usually I get to like
three of them and then there's enough
questions from the the the crowd and
tangents that uh I don't answer
everything you write down but it is uh
the nice way that we keep rolling it
does give me a starting point uh for
going into the Q&A lectures so uh we're
going to do plot first uh I kind of go
back and forth on where I start I should
say back and forth and further forth uh
because there's a
stories are built up generally of three
things they are built up of your plot
your setting and your character and the
intersection of plot setting and
character is conflict what you're
looking for is how to create that
conflict and as far as stories go co uh
setting plot and character all should
exist to create some sort of conflict or
to facilitate some sort of conflict
because that's what your story is about
um so I'm going to talk a little bit I
actually took notes this time um yes I
know look at that
um so what's the purpose of plot right
why why what do we talk about when we
mean plot I often talk about plot in
kind of two different categories and I
label them big p plot and Little P plot
a capital P plot and uh and a little p
plot capital P plot is when someone says
what is your book
about that's what you tell them this is
the what you can boil it down to in a
sentence or two plot what is the Lord of
the Rings about uh it's about a furry
footed British dude taking a magic green
and trying to throw it in a pit right uh
that's the the funny way of putting you
but you know what I mean like what is
the Lord of the Rings about trying to
over destroy saaron through destroying
this r that is the the conflex of his
power Little P plot is what happens
chapter by chapter in order to keep the
reader
engaged so the plot of low of the Rings
might be destroy the ring but the lower
cast Casp plot might be all right um
there's um some Orcs here and we can't
get past them what do we do well we'll
dress up like them right like that sort
of thing uh how it's the the small
little problem and then you resolve it
small little problem you resolve it
building toward larger problems that
you're hopefully resolving next week
we're going to talk about plot
Frameworks So today we're not going to
talk about the hero's journey or plot
archetypes or things like that instead
we're going to talk about the general
idea of what plot is for and in my mind
plot is for a couple of things first is
for facilitate conflict it's going to be
the primary way that you create conflict
in your story a thing needs to
happen and the characters need to do it
and something is standing in their way
pretty obvious um the second thing
though a plot is there to give the
reader some structure to give the reader
some sort something to hang on to to to
give them a sense that a story is being
told and is moving along um
plot tends to be the one because of
these reasons that is the most difficult
to innovate
upon of plot setting in uh character I'd
say setting is the easiest place to
innovate character second easiest uh
plot is the most difficult um there are
various we'll talk about them um next
week various plot Frameworks but there's
certain things people expect in a
satisfying story and yes you can subvert
those and most of the ways you would
subvert those just makes your story
unsatisfying now you may want to tell an
unsatisfying story there are reasons to
do that but in general you're looking to
tell a satisfying story and there are
certain things that work for that and
certain things that don't and because of
that you'll notice that if you go on and
you know start googling plot and start
researching it people will be like
there's only three plots there's only
only seven plots there's only one plot
right um the hero's journey they um uh
he would be like yep there's one plot
it's been told uh in all these different
ways uh but he stretched a ton to make
that count I don't know how many plots
there are but I can tell you that
innovating here um is not necessarily
something that needs to be
done um in general if you are combining
your plot with interesting characters
and an interesting set and you have you
are kind of using what we're going to
talk about today in this class you're
going to create something that is going
to read and it's going to feel fresh and
unique right it doesn't matter that
Dune is Hamlet
right is The Lion King
right right down to the break in the
middle of Lion King and dune which I've
always found interesting that both of
them are like we're going to skip all
the growing up part right maybe it's cuz
Hamlet he was already grown and then
Hamlet skipped the whole first half of
the story and its hamlets the second
half but there's something about that
story son is wronged as father dies and
Uncle seizes the throne son goes away
and comes back stronger maybe crazier uh
in Hamlet's case uh and becomes a rival
for the for the uncle's Throne killing
the uncle and restoring order to The
Pride lands or whatever they call them
right uh to oracus um you would not look
at The Lion King and dune and and be
like wow those are the exact same story
even though the general concept the
general structure is the same structure
right you've probably I would guess
never thought that Dune was Hamlet uh
everyone talks about Lion King being
Hamil so you probably already knew that
one um but the fact that they share
these these very similar plot structures
even to the point that it's like the
uncle and things like this uh doesn't
make these stories feel unfresh or
unoriginal fact Dune is probably my
favorite book of all time um and so
because of
that you can use plot as a tool plot
should be in my opinion one of these
places where the chef knows what works
and can use it to their Advantage
without with only taking pieces and
parts you'll even notice like as I said
when Shakespeare wrote this uh story he
to tell the story he wanted to he
started with Hamlet arriving back right
well when Dune tells this story it backs
up and shows all of this and the the
wrongs being committed that need to be
writed um the stories are trying to do
different things um and so you know it's
uh in The Lion King you need cute Plucky
animal
Sidekicks in Dune you need an animal
that will eat you if you walk without
Rhythm so the different needs are
different for the different
stories now I think that plot breaks
down to this idea of Promise progress
and
payoff and all the Frameworks we'll talk
about next week and the ways of
constructing a plot will kind of rely on
this same concept you might be saying to
me Brandon I Am Naturally more of a
pantser I like to um I like to write by
the seat of my pants I don't like to
have a structure as I mentioned with
Stephen King he feels that if he makes
an outline he's already told his story
and it makes it harder for him to then
go tell his story because discovering
the story is part of what drives him to
write um don't worry you can do all of
this while Discovery writing um right
now the Frameworks we'll talk about next
week some of those if you're a discovery
writer you just don't want to use right
you don't want to sit down and use
seveno story structure um but the more
you learn about the Core Concepts of
what makes people read books and enjoy
them the more you can apply that as
you're discovering your story and one
thing to be aware of is the difference
between Discovery writers and outline
liners and again Everyone Falls on the
spectrum between and indeed most people
are little of both and it changes based
on Project most people spend about the
same amount of time the outliner spends
it up front the uh Discovery writer
spends it on the back end right and
these sorts of things we're talking
about are often really handy tools for
analyzing a story that's gone wrong in
fact that's kind of a theme for this
whole class
um when you sit down to write a lot of
times writers are not like are not
thinking what is the what is the
progress here right um I do because
that's how I analyze story but I think
most people are writing by Instinct and
then if something doesn't work writers
back up and say all right what's the
disconnect here and they will often
arrive at things that essentially mean
I've made a promise but my progress is
something different how do I fix that
well I go back generally and make new
promises because the progress that I'm
writing along is what I want to tell the
story about so don't worry and feel that
you have to learn all of this up front
and apply it to your outline before you
start writing your book writing will
teach you how to do this better than any
other activity will as we T talk about
talked about last week so take all of
these things use them as analytical
tools to help you begin understanding
story and if things are broken then
maybe you can analyze them according to
some the things we talk about and if
you're an outliner they might be really
handy in making your outlines so
questions on any of that before we talk
about uh
promises yes um how much of this is just
North American culture yeah um so how
much of this is uh is I would uh say uh
Western storytelling Traditions um right
but really modern Western storytelling
Traditions how much is it uh this is a
little bit hard for me to put a point on
because um definitely in um in Asia
Japan uh Korea China you're going to see
a different use of payoff most often
that's where they deviate the most uh
the payoff there based on kind of subtle
uh story storytelling archetypes over
time mean something different and is
what is satisfying to that audience can
be different that said they are
homogenizing whether for good or for ill
you are seeing more and more of
ambiguous endings being more popular in
the the west and you're seeing more
payoff endings uh in the East and both
are kind of viable it just depends on
what kind of payoff that you want to
have you still generally use um in some
of the the Eastern style storytelling
even going back if you're going to read
Journey to the West right you're going
to see see kind of the same progress and
promise methodology you're just going to
see very different payoff methodology uh
excellent question um so yeah go ahead
just just out of curiosity when you're
writing something like when you've been
writing something longer like Stormlight
or something where would you put
yourself on the scale between Discovery
and outliner Discovery and outliner so
um every author uh then the question is
so it can be repeated for the the camera
um where like on Stormlight in
particular would I put myself um between
outliner and pancer or whatever um every
author is a pancer is a discovery
writing at the core as they're working
right even if you have bullet points
you're still Discovery writing like
nobody's outline is as long as their
story so you're always Discovery writing
something um I remember a famous uh
story that I was told that I have not
been able to confirm I tried very hard
and I think it might just be apocryphal
but the story I was told when I was
young is that in uh the movie ET the
screenplay just said Elliot and ET
escape on the bikes right and uh at
least in one of the drafts and then that
became the most iconic scene in the film
a lot of times your outline will say the
characters escape and then you have to
Discovery write that right so the
outliner you know it's it's a bit of a
misnomer to call anyone true truly an
outliner cuz it's just how much pancing
you are uh comfortable with uh I tend to
fall much more on the outlining side for
everything and the longer the series The
more detailed my outlines are um that is
because I'm kind of throwing myself
footballs and then trying to catch them
15 years later right
um and the better guess I have where I
am uh the easier will be to catch those
footballs that said I knock out walls
that I would have considered loadbearing
uh and I change things around and as you
write uh the story matures and so even
myself who I consider myself one of the
more hardcore outliners that I know um I
would say that more Discovery writer
than outliner in general just compared
to other people I outline more and
here's a fun thing for you here's
anecdote time and then I'll get to this
question
um I have been on many panels on writing
and I generally find
myself one of the few outliners this has
changed over time I find that there are
more outliners now than there used to be
uh but I still tend to be in the
minority and so I talk about myself as
kind of being odd sometimes as such a
strong outliner I once sat on a panel in
Germany me and I kid you not I said this
and uh like how I do it and all the
Germans looked at me and they're like no
that's how it's
done I'm like no there's Discovery
writing they're like horrified they're
like people do that without a structure
um I I thought it was funny it's a
little bit of stereotype but it
literally happened that all the Germans
are like the it's insane to not have an
outline um so all right question here
and then we'll go we'll do this one then
we'll do uh yeah how you to terms with
dropping plots or plans that you feel
are C your how do you come to terms with
dropping plots or plans that you feel a
core to your story how do you come to
terms with killing Your Darlings which
is a famous uh screenwriting uh
terminology for this sort of
thing you tell yourself a lie okay I'm
going to tell you what the LIE is I will
find a much better place for this
character plot or idea where it can
shine in its own story and then nine
times out of 10 you won't because that
idea actually wasn't that great you just
built the whole story upon it the story
then evolves because the process of
building a story is where the real
creativity takes off and as you start
writing it you start applying all of
your ideas and that that thing that
started you actually is not as good as
the rest of it and part of you realizes
it once in a while that one out of 10
that lets you have plausible deniability
on your your lifee once in a while that
one out of 10 becomes its own story and
it deserves that space and time I I will
say this um just as a blanket I almost
always throw away my first chapter often
my first several chapters of a given
book and write them over once I'm
finished this is how you can tell even
though I'm an
outliner Discovery writing and really
focusing on the progress side of this
which is in many ways the most important
but the least showy right it's the one
that people will pay attention to to the
least but it's 90% of your book um once
you know what that progress is you then
know how to signpost that for people to
enjoy it and throwing away your early
chapters is really common in the
industry so this is one of the reasons
why it's best not to become where's Nate
not to become an eternal hey you were
right there and I just looked past you
not to learn as Nate has done to not
keep revising your first chapter until
you finished your book because for most
of us you won't really be able to do
that until you've gotten far enough
along to know how to make those promises
so thank you for being two years running
my really great example uh on this so
all right I'm going to go into to
promises then we will do more Q&A okay
so promises promises are the easy one
okay
you should not stress Promises at the
beginning of your book Because Why once
you learn your progress and once you've
written an ending and if you're a
discovery end writer it'll be a bad
ending don't stress that either once you
know what the core of your book is about
throwing away three chapters and
rewriting it so that your promise Nails
what you want to do uh in your story is
easy throwing away 40 chapters in the
middle is hard right if you just look at
the the weight of time so but promises
in many ways are the most important
they're the easiest but most important
why are they most important well you
might have heard um people talk about
how important your hook or your first
line is and things like that I find
rarely the first lines actually
matter um we like to talk about them
usually it's your first couple of pages
really matter and yes a Zinger of a
first line can be really great right um
you know what what what is the the the
the the great ones you can go look at
some of the great ones what's that call
is call me Ismail is a really great
first line uh snow crash has a really
great first line um you know 1984 has a
really great first line right like
there's a bunch of really great first
lines they're awesome
having one of those is worth doing but
really your first chapter your first few
pages they are important because that's
where someone's going to decide whether
or not to put your book down and that's
dangerous and it's also dangerous for
you because most of the books you
read the authors are actually relying on
something before the first line to not
make you put the book down and that is
the name on the title right so when you
pick up the way of kings and you read
the way of
Kings I can get away with so much in
that
book because I'm trading on my name and
popularity right um like how do I pitch
way of Kings I say this is the book to
read once you trust
me you might trust me because your
friend won't leave you alone and wants
you to read it you might trust me
because you tried a different book once
you trust me you can read the way of
Kings it has three prologues that's a
terrible idea don't do
that right only one of them's named
prologue but I cheated and named one
Prelude right and then the next chapter
is a prologue also um it's just called
chapter one um it really is that's if
you haven't seen that's the one from
from the eyes of the kid who's on the
battlefield it's not even you know a
main character right um so so don't do
that
unless what you are willing to get the
ad yeah how should I say unless you're
willing for people to just put your book
down you got a question on this um I do
with promises how in your in larger
series yes how do you keep promises
between books how do you keep promises
between books change people between
books and you can't do that by making a
promise each book yes you can you can
make it the promise each book but a lot
of times it depends on the structure of
your story all right a lot of romance
novels do this by saying here is an
whole family of unmarried young eligible
people book one's about the eldest gu
what book book two is about right
inherent structure you can promise that
in your first chapter if you if you do
it right so that everyone knows oh it's
going to be a seven book series cuz
there's seven girls right um and then
there's cousins so we're going to keep
going um that's how you know if a series
made money if Cousins start getting
married I'm joking but it's real um so
uh but you can also do that like if you
are an established author there is a
promise that this is the first of a
Trilogy people are picking it up the
actual packaging of the book can give
you your promise of sort of structure um
in the The Wheel of Time Robert Jordan
Promises at the end of this book series
The Dragon reborn will fight the the
dark
one he said he'd get there in three
books when he pitched it to Tom dhy I
have that straight from Harriet his wife
he thought he could do it in three books
um and the the first book was going to
end with him taking the sword that was
not a sword from the stone that's not a
stone right if you've read the series
that's book three and then it just got
longer from there um Discovery writers
this is what happens when Discovery
writers get series um so um but he made
that promise right often times if you
have a big series it can be really handy
to make one of the kinds of promises the
kinds of promises can be um this is a
large Continuing Story and there's
something cool at the end it can be here
are Seven Sisters it can be these are
the continuing Adventures of said
character then you just name your series
something like the blank and blank files
or the blank of Blake you know the Dron
files are a great example of this right
um then each one is going to be a
contained Adventure that's your promise
right you can do all of these things but
may you be so lucky as to have to worry
about this let's talk about the promises
you should be worrying more about right
now because you're going to be looking
at making a couple of big promises in
the beginning of your story and they
don't they aren't all in innately
obvious the first is you often want to
make a tone promise okay a tone promise
is separate from the plot promises that
you're uh otherwise making what is a
tone promise well a tone promise is a
way to tell the reader this is the kind
of story you're getting into uh and this
is the sort of feel that it's going to
have if your story is going to involve a
lot of humor you want there to be jokes
early on if this is a story about
tragedy and it being Grim dark well you
start your story with a Viewpoint
protagonist who gets beheaded by someone
who doesn't want to kill him right Game
of Thrones right um right if you want
you know you you give a tone promise
through descriptions naming your
characters the Stark family is a tone
promise um that George Martin made in
those books um whereupon if you're going
to name your wizard School Hogwarts and
the your your Gandalf was name
Dumbledore you are giving a promise of
Whimsy right uh and things like this the
way that you're naming things the way
you're introducing your stories um the
way you're you're using your Pros in
your opening is going to give someone an
important promise about what your story
is about this is why the prologue became
a really big thing in Epic Fantasy
because Epic Fantasy wanted to start its
plot slow uh Epic Fantasy generally
leans on this sort of um progression
fantasy that is you know like a lot of
the um a lot of the the lit rpgers do
this very explicitly these days um if
you don't know what that is it's it's a
very popular genre particularly in Indie
publishing where you add your characters
have like bars of experience bars and
level and things like that like they're
in a video game um but most epic fantasy
is the story of the young nobody who
ends up saving the world I wouldn't say
most but a large number of the the very
popular ones it's the uh the traditional
Heroes Journey sort of thing those
stories tend to start with a young
person standing and looking up at the
Suns and imagining a world Beyond right
um but because of that that's not the
tone of the whole story the tone of the
whole story is we're getting chased by
space
Wizards and things are exploding so what
do these stories do they add a prologue
that that is basically there to give you
a tone promise we start with the door
being blasted off and Laser fire and a
dark Samurai coming through the smoke
and you know using magical powers and
then we cut to Young
idealistic uh every man standing and
being like wow what's beyond the stars
the answer is space Wizards and lasers
but you know that and he doesn't yet um
one of the most masterful uses of this
is Robert Jordan's Wheel of Time um
which is going to start with a young man
on a farm and things are going to feel
creepy right it does feel creepy but the
main story is uh the story of what
happens if you get too much power and
you might kill everyone that you love
but you need that power to save the
world that is the basic premise so what
does he do prologue hey there's a person
who has all this power but has gone
crazy and killed everyone he loves right
um you will see this very commonly as
one of your ways to make a tone promise
uh to the point that it's almost a
now so you need to be using it carefully
don't do it just cuz it's done do it
because your story really benefits from
it and be aware that if there are lots
of people doing it then it's harder to
stand out doing it that said I did it in
Stormlight I didn't in mistborn right um
I used that kind of tone promise
prologue for different reasons that's
why Stormlight has two uh prologues
here's one tone for the whole series
Melancholy about these people who have
been Immortal and things are falling
apart next tone promise hey
assassinations and Wars um and then you
know yeah so what's that yes and then
yeah then number three oh the poor kid
on the battlefield that's going to be a
that's going to come back isn't it
um hey yes I knew why I did each of
those prologues but uh but yeah it is a
lot it is a lot to swallow um so
other reasons things that your promises
you're going to make some stories choose
and you don't need to do this but some
Cho stories choose to do an opening what
we call a cold open which is actually
what Star Wars is do starting in midor
res right at the beginning but they
often will do this little mini story at
the beginning and the purpose of this is
to say here is our story in
microcosm we're going to do it in five
15 pages and then we're going to do it
in 150 Pages uh Indiana Jones
love to do this right um the first one
is really excellent this Indiana Jones
cool Adventurer going to overcome trials
it's going to be really hard for him but
he's going to be he's going to use his
wits and his whip uh to overcome these
and at the end he's going to
lose right that is the opening uh to
Indiana Jones and the Raiders the Lost
AR um and then the rest of the movie is
the exact same thing done a second time
at length in slightly different ways uh
you will see this used pretty commonly
as your sort of Promise of here's what
my story is often when you have a cold
open that's what the cold open is for
here's our characters pulling a heist so
you can know how good they are at
pulling Heist and then we're going to
use that either H to replicate it or
something's going to go wrong with the
next Heist so you knew how it's supposed
to go and then this whole story is about
how it what happens when it goes wrong
um excellent ways to kind of introduce
your characters and things like that
sometimes your opening does that um a
lot of times you want your opening to
give you a promise of what the plot of
the story is going to be even if you
don't do it in microcosm um you want to
introduce some metaphor for the main
conflict and this is difficult sometimes
because sometimes your main conflict
won't come until much later sometimes it
will for instance Star War
hey it's right up there we need to get
the Death Star plans we're going to blow
up the Death Star boom in the cold open
and in the tone promise you've got it
all um sometimes though you don't right
like what is Lord of the Rings are we
going to find out the plot of Lord of
the Rings well it kind of has the mini
thing you gather your group of friends
it's really hard you get to this place
um that's uh Rivendell and then you do
it again and it takes three books that
time um but a lot of times your
characters like not going to discover
what the big problem is until around the
end of act three if you're using the ACT
structure this is a problem for giving a
promise about the plot what do you do
well sometimes you just let the tone
promise hold handle it sometimes you
spend those opening things saying here's
the tone of the book here's my character
and why you should like them now we'll
introduce a problem that is really hard
to overcome and that is fine you don't
have to promise all of these things
sometimes you try to find a mini way to
introduce what the character's conflict
or the main conflict might be in that
opener uh what am I talking about with
these sorts of things well sometimes you
will read a book or see a film um where
a character is trying to fix a broken
down hunk of junk and then you know I
mean the Transformers movies do this
it's about I need a car Dad car car car
oh it's hard I found this car well the
movie is going to be about cars and
getting cars and you kind of have this
little mini introduction to what the
character wants and why they can't have
it um and this is really kind of what
you're introducing in this opener if
you're trying to get to kind of your
character promises is what do they want
what do they need why can't they have it
and you can kind of start there and then
throw the capital P plot at them at the
at the end of act one as long as your
lowercase p plot kind either gives a
promise of tone or is in microcosm some
ex some sort of picture small snapshot
of the larger picture that is going to
become the book this is why all of this
can be done pretty easily in retrospect
right once you know where you're going
you can start making these promises a
lot easier so I'm going to go off of
promises for a second but I'm going to
let you ask me questions first and I'm
going to look and see what um yes I
think I got to it all yeah um what about
just like skipping the entire first part
of your story Al together yeah it's done
it's done uh anything can be done and it
can be done well right I mean I just
referenced Hamlet Hamlet essentially
skips of what most people would do it
skips act one of this very classic story
that I would be willing to bet during
Shakespeare's time because this is how
Shakespeare worked he had heard that
story I mean it's a really common story
to be to telling you know the the prince
who has to reclaim his kingdom from the
person who over through it through it
he' heard that story uh and he chose to
skip act one and start uh with act two
uh which is weird I'm talking story
structure act not playwriting acts which
are different in that case right same
terminology but they mean different
things so this happens all the time you
will um you will you've probably seen
Min a story Monkey Island too does this
um there's a deep cut Monkey Island uh
um where you have a character start with
some interesting thing happening and
then record scratch you're probably
wondering how I got here emperor's new
grp right um right and then they tell
act one in flashback catching you up to
often times the middle of act two or
sometimes even the end of act two and
then they launch into uh you know that
you've probably seen that but there are
plenty of stories like Hamlet that just
say pick it up from Context we aren't
doing act one we're in the middle of a
story um in fantasy I would say that the
Malazan Book of the Fallen loves to do
this just like boom we're going figure
out where we are uh if you can so yeah
totally doable um yeah what if you
switch between tones back and forth
deliberately like from more of a
thriller tone to kind of a travel log
and then back into a thriller as the
story progresses yeah um excellent
question what do you want what do you do
if you going to be switching between
tones your example being a pretty good
one of travel log Thriller travel log
Thriller um so you can promise both of
that at the beginning and I would really
suggest that you do uh you can do
anything you don't have to give any
promises famously the big breaker of all
of these rules is Into the Woods if you
haven't uh seen into the woods it like
it starts off it's like here's all these
people on their adventures and then
promises are stomped flat uh when you
come back from the intermission goodbyes
promises sometimes literally stomp flat
um and uh the thing about that is he
very cleverly does something we're going
to talk about in twists where he makes
you want the pro tone to change and and
so often times there's that but with
this sort of story you could give it uh
you could make promises at the beginning
something in microcosm that's like you
know this story is about these kinds of
things it's always more difficult more
difficult things make you grow and if
you do them right when you break the
rules here's here's kind of a a rule of
thumb that you could therefore break I
don't know here's a rule of thumb things
that break the rules have a harder um a
bigger threshold to overcome to grab the
readers attention but once they do they
tend to have a stronger and more
dedicated following right blandness
tends to get fewer dedicated
followers um
whereas something that is that is doing
what it shouldn't but makes it work
tends to When It Go gets big tends to to
be very big um and this is a reason why
for instance there are within some
genres um let's use r Rance within
romance there are uh some very
formulaic stories that people still read
and love right but they don't really
capture people you read them you dispose
of them you read the next and dispose of
them the ones that break the rules a
little bit uh it ends with us as a great
example of this it's not really a
romance novel um but kind of is but kind
of isn't suddenly when those take off
they can take off really big because
they are are standing out they are
breaking those rules but they have uh
they take more inertia I I always say
I'll get to you but I got a question
back there after this I always say that
books all of them have like these
certain red marks against them right uh
and all every great book has a ton of
these your job is not to get rid of all
the red marks a red mark being something
that would make someone put the book
down make it harder to get into your job
is to get rid of the ones that aren't
integral to the piece of art you're
making and then you try to rely on the
ones that are that that are integral you
can't get rid of to be things that also
distinguish it way of Kings has three
prols what does way of Kings get from
that well it's really hard to get into
if you're going to put down the way of
Kings you're like most of my books if
you read the onear reviews they're very
different for the way of Kings the
onestar reviews just could not get
through the first uh 10 chapters too
much going on too many names too many
characters and Callin is way too
depressed um right
uh but because of that I can start
really low and go really high I can then
World builds so much that when it all
clicks together and you get it it's so
distinctive and interesting it's not
like anything you've read I'm able to do
things with this red mark that you could
not do with a book that didn't have it
so as long as you are using them to
their fullest yes they will break the
rules right now to sell in fantasy they
say we want $120 ,000 words traditional
published wave of Kings is 400 right
elrus was 250 when I submitted and I got
down to 200 as long as you're earning
that 200 then suddenly it becomes does
that make sense so um so yeah uh let's
go back here and then up here and then
we'll see where we are where there was
one back there in the corner and I
didn't want to ignore you because it's
hard to see so yeah um about promises
and like you said that the first two
chapters are easy to you know edit after
the fact you find your also editing a
lot in the middle um keeping up with
your promises that you found you made it
end well that's more progress we'll talk
about progress next so I'm glad you
asked that um I'm not doing as much
mostly I'm trying to make the ending and
the promise match what is the
interesting parts of the middle is
really what I'm shooting for but I'm a
bad example on this because I generally
know my ending so my progress and my
ending usually align pretty well it's
just nailing the right promise at the
beginning is easier after I've actually
written that ending all right down here
how do you like how
do scale with like length store like say
like have like a shorter store like for
installment in like athology how does
that scale so how to promises scale with
length of the story the example being
you've got a smaller piece maybe part of
Anthology or a short story um so in a
short story and maybe we'll try to get
Eric in during one of the weeks I'm gone
to talk short stories everything just
has to be trimmed down but and it also
has to be distilled it's not just a
matter of writing shorter it's writing
in a more distilled way so you still
need to hit that promise in some ways
you need to hit it harder it because it
does need to be like in your first
paragraph in the short story um rather
than the fantasy book where you can
spend a whole prologue giving us a tone
promise and then switch characters just
can't do that in a short story right or
you could you can do anything but in
most short stories I wouldn't recommend
it so therefore um what you're trying to
do is you're hitting it just really hard
in a long story you can do what I did
and have three separate chapters doing
three separate promises um right before
you even start your book readers will
look at the length of your book and they
will determine how long they'll give you
to start getting around to it based on
that length yeah can you and should you
make new promises as you progress
through this can you and should you make
new promises as you progress to the
story the answer is yes and yes asteris
right uh depends on how long your story
is and it tends on depends on what kind
of twists you're going for all most
stories will be making new promises
you'll be interesting a new charact
introducing a new character and you're
going to make a promise about that
character usually every character is
going to have some innate promises
attached to them uh usually this is with
their character Arc right uh and we'll
talk about this in uh probably actually
sanderson's Second Law um but the idea
is you're going to attach to them flaws
handicaps and challenges right uh and
you're going to like you know you're
going to figure out what you're going to
signpost which of those are going to be
overcome which of them are going to be
expunged which where the character is
going to grow or fail to grow right um
and so every characters but each little
plot sequence will often have a promise
in fact every chapter generally has one
uh often times chapters just like
unfortunately as frustrating as it is to
go back to your high school classes your
teacher like thesis paragraph a lot of
the best chapters start with a stealth
thesis paragraph that introduces what
the chapter's going to be about and what
you're going to learn and then at the
end we'll have a stinger of a line that
indicates you know now you've learned it
right but it depends on the type of plot
that you have we'll get to that in
progress all right where are we um I
need to move to progress we're going to
move to progress if there's time at the
end I'll take more questions but we got
we got progress and progress is the most
important of them and so save your
question and when I do questions at the
end after payoffs you can reference back
okay but let's talk progress all right
so my notes yes yes NES
um
so you
absolutely control progress in your
story to a greater extent than you
think it's pretty easy to explain this
right uh at any point in your story
let's say you're writing a romance you
could write he stopped being stupid and
so they got together and got married the
end at any point you can just write that
at any point tolken could have written
uh and to Bilbo fell through a wormhole
appeared in in midor and dropped the
ring into the thing and everyone was
saved right you've maybe read stories
where at the ending a writer rushed this
a little too much and you felt a little
bit like froto had been dropped Through
the Wormhole um right
uh we call that a deox Machina right um
You control time and progress absolutely
in your story you as a writer I could
give you the challenge right now to say
all right you need to spend 50 pages and
only one second can
pass it would be really boring but you
could all do it right you just describe
everything in the room uh right and and
then get into philosophy it's in the
character head and then you know do a
flashback or whatever you can you could
you do 50 pages in one second is passed
I bet you've read books for feel like
that
before uh those of you like manga here
there's lots of filler uh uh chapters
sometimes um yeah so you can also be
like and a thousand years past I've read
books that use uh structures like this
right um You control time you control
progress so your job as a writer is not
to make things pro uh progress it is to
give a sense of satisfying progression
through a
story and you do this by deciding a
couple of things first is how fast your
progress is going to be your short story
is going to go faster you're also going
to if you're
writing say a thriller um you're writing
a story where a lot of the opposition is
external
obstacles to overcome characters got to
fight this grab this get to this place
right I mean tenant is this um it's
almost all external and it's the next
problem the next problem next problem
those stories are paced very differently
from the story about a character
wrestling with whether or not it's right
to kill your uncle um you know or how
you would kill your uncle and you know
if you'd even make a good king or you
know
H how how awful it is that you're
driving your girlfriend and saying like
all of this stuff you're wrestling with
all this um right that's a that has a
very different pacing you're going to
decide kind of how your pacing is and
it's nice to match it to your story and
to your own natural writing style so how
fast you want to go the most important
thing you'll probably decide is what
kinds of progress you're going to make
and how you're going to signpost that to
the
reader so this is a little bit of a hard
one to explain so give me some time on
this there are lots of different types
of progress you can make in a story and
you want to generally match that to what
your climax is going to be for instance
if you are telling what is basically a
mystery plot which doesn't mean you're
writing a mystery but you're plot is
based around characters lacking
information and needing to find this in
information and your ending you're going
to in is going to involve a big
informational reveal the mystery uh
story is obviously the best example of
this right uh who done it we have a
murder we know somebody did it we don't
know who it is the detective is going to
over time sort through and discover
Clues and at the end reveal who did it
information style plot right a lot of
stories have Mysteries built into them
in these cases your progress is measured
by
information what Clues have been given
what suspects have been discovered and
which ones have been eliminated you
therefore often want to find ways to
signpost that progress is being made you
can do this in a lot of ways if it's a
mystery the detective is saying I've
almost got this I feel like I'm so close
uh you will watch a lot of mystery
stories do this we're getting closer
we're almost there we need but one more
piece Watson um right and there are
these signposts that are saying you are
making you are you were getting there
and you are at the same time giving this
information to the reader a relationship
plot
which buddy cop movies and romantic
comedies follow the same structure for
these right um it's just whether there's
a fist bump or a kiss at the end
um in these sorts of stories what you're
going to be doing is the relationship is
going to be making progress you're going
to start off with the with a very clear
indication these people do not get along
and then you're going to show ways that
they do but then there's going to be
back steps occasionally but then you're
going to through the course of the story
be like wow these two people work better
together than they ever did a part they
are filling holes in each other's lives
and so when they finally get together
that's your
Climax and I the the trick with this is
stories often have multiples of these
going on at the same time that are
different things and identifying which
is the most important to your story and
therefore the key component to your
ending is actually really important
Guardians of the Galaxy is ostensibly an
adventure story about get the
McGuffin and prevent the world from
ending but the real story is can these
people work together and almost
everything that is not an action scene
and even some of the action scenes is a
relationship plot and so that movie
really cleverly has its climactic moment
being where the main character who's
refused to take his mom's hand when she
wanted to give him a hug when she was
dying takes the hand of his friends and
they all take each other's hands and
then together that you know with a dance
battle is what beats the bad guy right
it is not necessarily that you know the
McGuffin beats the bad guy it is
literally the power of
friendship that defeats the bad guy and
that when a plot really works it that
what happens and to do this what gets
really tricky is you sometimes have to
identify the difference between kind of
the trappings of your
story and your a plot and your B plot
and what people are going to think they
are Guardians is a great example people
like ostensively your big p plot is
actually get the
McGuffin chase down the McGuffin get
them in the guffin clear our names um to
prevent the world from being destroyed
but the actual little PE plot is
character um is a is can we get along
can we become friends uh and so you're
going to have multiples of these and
usually want to pay them off alt
together you just kind of have to decide
what your soul of your story is uh the
longer your story The more souls of your
story that you can have and often you
can introduce things like this have a
whole Arc about people you know becoming
friends and then go into act three
and solve the McGuffin problem uh
guardians of galaxy doesn't do this
doesn't WR on top of each other but you
can do things like that you've probably
read stories where for instance Moana
Moana has a you know a a subarc for Maui
in the middle of it uh it's handled
that's a really good movie but it's
handled kind of clunkily with Maui's
return but they're trying to do this
right they're trying to have like we're
not going to do this at the main climax
just right before it so Maui has his
character climax at and comes back uh
and things like this so figuring out and
identifying what your various plots are
and how you're going to make them all
have a sense of progress is really vital
I think uh for making a story work a
page Turner is usually a story that
really understands progress and how to
dull it out a boring book when people
get you know when you don't write it on
purpose like I did um
I th those who aren't laughing I
literally released a book called the
most boring book ever last year um it
was a kid's book though
um
um where a a book that people like
boring or I got lost usually the
signpost of progress are not there now a
big reason the signpost of progress
cannot be there is that you gave someone
a really interesting promise and then
you as a writer got really interested in
something else and you have a giant
subplot going somewhere else that
doesn't seem to advance the main story
The Last not yeah the Last Jedi does
this um as a film um you know Last Jedi
does this and so what happens is Finn as
a character has been introduced to us in
the first movie and then reintroduced to
us in the second movie as a guy who
cares about his friend Ray and really
wants to go find her and help her and
then the plot says you know I did
promise that but what if you let some
horses Go
free what if you really needed to learn
that horses should be
free and Finn's like
uh my friend Ray the fate of the
universe uh Luke Skywalker blah blah I
want to go to my friend Ray and the
plot's like H but those
horses um
and not everyone had this experience but
it was a lot of people and it was the
experience I had like why are we here
what are we doing I am not feeling that
this is progressing the promises made to
me by this story and so whatever is
interesting happening
there we don't invest in I had this
problem in
oathbringer um where I'll try to explain
it without giving too many spoilers I
had a plot I'm going to draw on the
board for
you a little harder to draw on the board
in this uh in this
one um all right oh I'm supposed to use
black because the uh the camera can pick
it up better so you all know to take
your quiz it's already passed right no
no no no it's 7:45 not 845 yeah it's all
passed you all
fail so sorry come back next year
um so I had a story where characters
were right here and I needed that knew
they needed to be right there right
characters all are kind of set a drift
they don't know what they're doing
they're in a new environment um they
land here and um they all are like well
if we can get to this place then we can
get out of here and so they all make a
plan to go to this place and then I have
them going there and then they get
diverted by something and then they get
diverted and who they end up where I
knew they needed to be all along readers
were so bored with this
plot right which was shocking to me
because the new environment that i' put
them in I'd done a lot of World building
the sort of things that make my stories
Pop I had put in there this is why we
will talk about it World building is
actually the least important of the
three it is I'm
sorry great world building with a bad
characters and Bad plot is an encyclop
IIA right great characters and great
plot with a bad with bad World building
is still often an excellent book you can
probably name them the fact that time
termers break the entire universe of
Harry Potter wide open does not prevent
that from being the strongest book in
the entire Series
right right amen so World building is
important don't get me wrong you ideally
want to do all three but really great
world building cannot save a sequence
where you have said hey people need to
go to uh point B and then you send them
to point C because the whole time the
readers will be thinking this is a side
quest and we are being diverted from our
story until we start heading toward
point B where we'll be making progress
again because we are making no progress
I will not invest in this plot cycle
because it doesn't seem like it means
anything my solution was actually pretty
easy my solution was to have the primary
Viewpoint protagonist of this um right
near the beginning be put in conflict
with the rest of the group because he's
been told by a source that he believes
that if he doesn't get to Point C
someone he loves will die and he
believes that so strongly and he's the
main character we're seeing Through The
Eyes of right here or at least one of
them that Suddenly It's a it's like oh
are we supposed to go to B or C oh I
think we need to get to C because the
consequences of not getting to see if
this character is Right are really
really really dire so even though he's
in conflict with them it works and
suddenly that little change and suddenly
the whole plot sequence worked in the
next group of readers nobody had
problems everybody was enjoying it all
the things that I wanted to have happen
uh on wanted to be enjoyed were enjoyed
this such little changes and Promises
you see how I whoever asked you want to
make promises I made another promise in
the middle of the story promise is if
you don't get here something bad will
happen um and so he needs to get there
and so you can see how just little
diversions with really interesting
things can end up not working if you
don't understand progress payoff most of
the time not all the time most of the
time if a book is boring or if people
people aren't investing in a sequence
that you thought they should invest in
you have made a misalignment of progress
and
promise how consistent should we be with
ping throughout the book uh it depends
on your own personal style how question
is how consistent should you be on
pacing um it really really depends right
generally if you want to use Thriller
pacing which is you're going to write
short chapters you're going to try to
put a hook at the end of every one of
them or at least most of them um Dan
Brown is pretty good at this for all his
faults he's really good at this and
that's part of what made that dent code
work um is that short chapters with a
hook at the end of each one and a lot of
external conflict can really Propel a
story but they run out in my experience
right around 70,000 words and if you're
not going right into the climax then you
start to lose people uh so it works
really great for a story that's 90 to
100,000 words long really hard to keep
that up for too long because you
generally in a book want um you want
slowdowns in pacing for the reader to
get a breather for the characters to get
a breather and for you to kind of come
to um come to you know process what's
been discovered so that then you can
ramp it back up because variation is
noticeable and lack of variation creates
sort of a um a sense that you're
coasting along and it starts to lose its
impact if every sentence is a one
sentence Zinger then none of them right
what's that syndrome said if everyone
has superpowers nobody does or something
like that right um and it yeah if
everyone's super nobody is yeah there
you are uh sorry Brad Bird uh misquoting
you um
so there is an example of why you would
want to do both but if you can keep it
up like a lot of things people like this
is an absolute page term it's 80 to
100,000 words of just Relentless
plotting that you're supposed to read in
one sitting and not sit and not stop I
don't do that in The Stormlight Archive
um right um I did it a little bit in
wind and Truth uh which is why the
pacing feels different in wind and Truth
um than it does in other books uh so
it's really kind of up to you um what
you want to do with this generally no
you don't want the same pacing through
uh a book generally you want to change
pacing and have breathers and things
like this it's up to you um some books
are just really slow the whole time um
and that's just the author's writing
style right so yeah excellent question
go ahead yeah how do you deal with uh
speeding up progress when you want to
the characters to get to a destination
but you don't want to like take time
with the traveling right how do you
speed up progress when you want to um
not have to take time traveling I would
give
a mini promise early in your book that
sometimes you're just going to time
Jump um and then just time Jump just say
and then they arrived uh and you can do
this pretty easily um like if you're
having problems with people being like
Oh it feels like I missed too much end
part
one with and then start part two with
them having arrived stuff like this like
actual structural physicality breaks
like if you break a chapter and then say
3 weeks later so much easier for a
reader than if you try to in the middle
of a chapter say and 3 weeks P that said
uh Joe Rowling does it all the time in
Harry Potter and three weeks passed and
it was Christmas time now um and so you
I don't think you have to worry about
this as much as you think you do as long
as you've kind of established early on
um that you're going to you know like if
you even have one chapter that says at
the end of chapter 2 and then chapter 3
is like 3 Days Later X you've already
established this as a pattern uh and
nobody should ever have a with um you
know at sometimes you even do it right
at the end of a chapter you're
like over the next 3 days um she kept
worrying that something was going to
happen but at last they crested the hill
and saw boom and you've done it in a
paragraph so yeah uh back here and then
we'll do some of you up here so you said
that proper pacing proper progress sign
posting yeah but you also warned against
not making promises your so
is I guess is the key to a good plot
twist proper sign posting uh so we'll
talk about plot twists and payoff in a
second but yes that's part of it the
real good thing of the the secret to
proper twists is generally to promise
someone something and then make them
wish you'd promis something
else all right uh so to explain this
we'll we'll do some others but do to
explain this since the question is here
I imagine twists working like you have
given some you promised someone a gift
for Christmas and you you you say I do
you like toy cars I'm going to get you a
toy car and then you put a package under
the Christmas tree and the twist is what
do they actually
open plenty of you've got yeah plenty of
stories give you a toy car and there is
nothing wrong with that right
one of the greatest books of all time is
Pride and Prejudice what is the first
line of Pride and
Prejudice truth
univers
single yeah first line is this is a book
about someone getting married right and
then oh twist nope there's no twist they
get married right there's complications
and escalations which are different from
twist and equally important in fact even
even more important you do not have to
have a Twist however if you want a Twist
as was uh guessed earlier here one of
the things you can do is you can
escalate you can over uh over um deliver
you promised a a toy card you give them
a real car right but one of the classic
twists is you say I'm going to get you a
toy car they're like heay and then
through the course of the story you show
them how cool planes
are to the point that they're like I I'm
going to get a toy car but boy I wish I
was getting a toy plane and then you
give them a toy plane um I usually use
an example the the movie While You Were
Sleeping I'm going to spoil while you
were sleeping I'm sorry
okay yeah it's a fantastic film that
uses twist perfectly in this sort of
style it's a romance woman is like
dreaming seeing this guy pass through
her toll booth cuz she works it like a
toll booth on the freeway and thinking
that's the guy someday I'd like Mary and
she blah blah blah blah blah and then
like he gets in a car wreck and she's
there and she like helps him and he
wakes up and she tells a lie cuz she's
like oh I'm his girlfriend but not
really meaning to tell that lie she just
was you know dreaming it or I'm his
fiance and then everyone's like he had a
secret fiance oh no she's like oh no now
everyone thinks I'm his fiance I don't
want to let them down uh hi Jinx and Sue
right and so this story is about oh I'm
pretending to be his fiance cuz he's
lost his memory and things like that or
he's in a coma and then he's like
whatever right um in the meantime while
he's in a coma uh Slash wakes up and his
lost his memory because there's your
escalation right rather than a Twist
it's escalation what what's going to
happen when he wakes up and the LIE
becomes revealed oh he doesn't remember
I had a fiance oh wow she's pretty oh
that's good uh right
like I'm glad my secret fiance is Sandra
Bullock um right um in the meantime
through the whole time
uh this is this is not uncommon right I
think the Wedding Singer does the same
thing uh she's been hanging out with his
brother and falling in love with his
brother that's the airplane right you
find out they match each other really
well and she doesn't actually match this
other guy at all even though you were
promised a toy car in scene one you
through the course of the film really
come to want a toy plane and then of
course the ending is she ends up with
the plane with the brother right um
right she the hinks continue to ensue
until they you know go to comical and
ridiculous well they start at comical in
ridiculous proportions they blow go
further than that and then boom the the
the wrap up and the twist is you get
your plane it's pretty well sign poost
that you're getting your plane but there
are plenty of books that do this uh more
subtly um not that while you're sleeping
is bad for not doing it subtly it's a
really excellent story um but you can do
that more subtly so that the twist is oh
wow this is what I always wanted and
this is actually the secret to why uh
into of the woods Works um cuz into the
woods shows you idealic fairy tales in
the beginning and then starts to put
cracks in them so that you start to not
necessarily want the fairy tale ending
and then boom second act happens and
everything gets smashed to split uh
splintering but then it's rebuilt as
something better so that it ends up
working it's a really gutsy move and a
lot of people really dislike into the
woods for that reason like my mom does
not like into the woods she's just like
give me a fairy tale that's what you
promised you lied to me
sonheim I'm never watching any your
plays again mostly CU they're about
people eating other people or
assassinating people and then there's
Westside Story but um she'll watch that
one um sorry does that make sense um
yeah what how much time we got we got
five minutes okay all right let's we got
do promises write your questions in here
let's just do payoffs for a little
little bit uh I've already done the most
important one which is what do you do
with twists right um but payoffs are
really just um giving people a
surprising yet inevitable fulfillment of
your promises you make it surprising
through a couple of ways one is the
twist but usually what you do to make it
surprising is you give them plausible
deniability you make them believe that
it won't happen and most stories get a
lot of mileage out of this um right like
a ton of mileage out of making the story
work so well that you worry you wonder
the if the character you're like oh is
the character actually going to succeed
you know we we were pretty sure that
froo is going to succeed and that the
the world is not going to end but then
when he get get uh gets uh stung by
sheab and dies you're like
wait wait maybe Frodo won't maybe Sam
will have to do this all by himself
that's horrifying right escalation um
and then we get Frodo back um but then
froto collapses uh then Sam has to carry
him right like things like this like you
keep getting these obstacles escalations
and through obstacles escalations and
the last one being red herrings you man
to make people think that they aren't
going to get what you promis them then
you do anyway that is your basic that's
what you generally do the twist works
really well also
um sometimes your surprising yet
inevitable um is built around this idea
that as you're going through your story
you forget the promise right my favorite
of The Lord of the Rings films is the
second film where the promise is right
the end look for me on the morning of
the fifth day right and this is a
beautiful sequence and this will kind of
be where I'll wrap up I love the second
movie and I like the third movie I like
the Thro of s part but the Battle of
Helms Deep versus the Min turth battle
um they work on very different axes it's
all about promises right in the Min
turth battle in the third film uh
because the plays out slightly
differently in the books so I use the
films um because they make a better
object lesson um and this is in the
third film minus terth They're Up
Against All Odds they are going to be
destroyed and the promise is if they
don't you know fight this off themselves
they will fail this is their last
resort and then they fight and they're
really strong and they can't do it and
then Aragorn shows up and saves them in
the second film it's the same thing
they're in this the this Bastion it's
their last resort if they don't win this
they're all going to die and then
Gandalf shows up and saves them the
difference in these plot Cycles is
promises in the second film Gandalf says
look for me on the morning of the fifth
day and Peter Jackson very expertly uses
it what's it it's what it's uh um it's
uh what's his name um
the is it Yer yeah it's no yeah it's y y
yeah I was gonna say fman it's not F
it's Yer um and I was gonna say oh it's
a it's um it's it's bones but it's not
bones it's yr because he's in a
different movie um um but we very
expertly has them leave it doesn't work
this way in the books but he expert has
them leave so you have hanging on the
mantle there this idea of oh there's an
army out there that was faithful to the
king until the king pushed them too far
and left and you have Gandalf saying
look for me on the morning of the 5ifth
day I still wish it were the third day
for mythological reasons right
right morning of the third day the
sunrise anyway um but it's it's the
morning of the fifth day I went looked
I'm like oh you you missed out could
have been third
um um because
anyway through the course of how awful
that fighting is awful in a good way and
how dark everything gets you forget like
Aragorn and gimbley and legal Los forget
that gandal has promised because it's so
dark and they're at their last stand and
they're going out to die and then
Gandalf shows up and it's just brilliant
and wonderful and you love it because
you remember and they give a voice
Stinger remember if you can do that you
don't need a Twist you can just make us
Forget by making it so dark that when
the light comes back and The Sun Shines
and the Orcs are like oh we can't see
because Gandalf might have magic we're
not sure um and they get ridden down and
they're saved you're like cheering
whereas when Aragon shows up the ghosts
I don't know if you guys have that I'm
like oh good the ghosts are there I'm
glad they didn't die but I'm not
cheering right ghosts did all the work
they should have just everyone should
have hid and waited for the ghosts um
and then the second one you're like ah
they had to fight every inch of the
ground they gave up so that they could
last long enough for gandal to show up
and that's what promis progress and
payoff mean is making this work so that
you have when these work people cheer
this people get cheer chills the story
just is magical for a minute when this
works and when it
doesn't well you have other things that
can carry your story but I really like
this in plotting and so that's why I
talk about it next week we'll talk about
actual plot Frameworks and strategies
thank you guys so
[Applause]
much e